welcome to another Godot recipe there
are many ways to handle cameras in 3d
first person third person fixed
perspective it all depends on what kind
of game you're making in this recipe
we'll look at how to make a camera that
can orbit a target while remaining
parallel to the ground let's get started
so here we have a camera setup and then
I have this window down here set to show
us a preview of what the camera sees now
let's say I wanted to tilt the camera up
a bit to look at something and then I
want to rotate to this side but when I
tilt it back down I'm now gonna be
misaligned and that's usually something
you don't want you want the camera to
stay level always parallel with the
ground regardless of how you rotate or
look up and down you don't want that
tilt to happen and so the solution to
this is something called a gimbal a
gimbal is a device that's designed to
keep an object always level like that
you would use them on ships back in the
old days to keep thee to keep a flat
surface level even as the ship is
rocking in the waves and so we're gonna
make a scene here and we're gonna start
with two spatial nodes so spatial and
then another spatial as a child and then
I'm going to add the camera as a child
of that so the spatial the outer one is
going to be our camera gimbal and then
the second one is going to be the inner
gimbal so we have the camera is a child
of the inner gimbal the inner gimbal is
a child of the camera gimbal and here's
how that's going to work let's go back
to preview so we can see what the camera
sees I'm gonna take the camera and I'm
going to just set its transform the Z to
about 4 so it's offset a little bit from
from where the center is so we're
looking towards the origin so the way
that the camera gimbal works is each of
these nodes is responsible for one axis
of rotation and it's going to be its
local mode so I'm going to turn this to
local mode here
so when we rotate we're only rotating
the nodes local axes not the global ones
so the outer node the camera gimbal node
only rotates in Y it is for us to rotate
horizontally and look at the center now
we're never gonna move this one on any
other axis okay
the inner gimbal is going to rotate on
its X and only on X so it tilts up and
down and so you see how it's X's are
changing so now say I'm angling down a
little bit if I switch back to the outer
one the outer one see how the X's are
still level for this one the outer one
only rotates in Y so now we're orbiting
around whatever object we're looking at
as long as we stick to that then there's
never gonna be a problem with our camera
not being level anymore you can see how
it's always staying pointing at the same
point and it's always parallel with the
ground to control the gimbal we're going
to use the W a s and D keys so I've
added input actions for those in the
input map and I've labeled them cam
underscore so we know these are the
input actions for controlling the camera
and then I've also added zoom in and out
for the up and down mouse wheel so now
let's add a script to this we're gonna
give it a variable here called rotation
speed
it's gonna control how fast the camera
rotates while we're holding the keys
down and we'll start with PI over 2
which is 90 degrees so that's 90 degrees
per segment is what that will be and
then we're going to in our process
function we're going to check the
keyboard input and I'm going to do it
this way we're gonna pass Delta and
along with it I'm gonna do it this way
because we're gonna also want to enable
mouse control after we do this so I'm
just going to start with keyboard so the
function to get to check keyboard input
needs to rotate those two spatial
depending on which Keys we pressed so
starting with we're gonna rotate the
outer gimbal that's the node that this
script is attached to around the y-axis
and so we're going to have a variable
here called Y rotation and then that's
going to get set by which key we press
so now we can rotate object local and we
want to rotate around the y axis and we
want to rotate by that Y rotation x
rotation speed times Delta and then for
the inner gimbal we want to rotate inner
gimbal around its local x axis so we're
gonna do the same thing here I'm gonna
copy and paste because I've copied and
pasted the input code just changed it to
the other input keys and we're rotating
around X this time and once we have that
result we're gonna have the inner gimbal
and we're gonna rotate object local but
this time around the x axis and then by
the same amount X rotation and that
should do it let's give it a try so
here's a test scene I've made with I
made a ground plane and I imported a
model so we have something to look at
and then I've instanced the camera
gimbal into this scene so when we play
it we can see that if I press the a and
D Keys I will rotate around and if I
press W and s my camera will pan up and
down left and right
so that's exactly what we want we're
staying centered on the center of the
ship but what you'll notice is that
since we haven't put any limits on it
you can rotate too far and go completely
upside down which is probably not
something that we want we want to
probably stop it around there and maybe
stop it at the ground so that you can't
rotate too far up and down we'll fix
that in our script will we're going to
say inner gimbal the rotation dot X we
want to clamp that and we want to clamp
it between not quite 90 degrees we don't
want to go fully up to 90 degrees so I'm
going to say
let's say around 1.4 and then zero and
what that's going to do is it's going to
make it so that when I pan up that's as
far up as I can go and when I go down I
go straight down to the ground now
because that plane is there at the exact
zero degrees here we can't see the plane
so you might want to limit it to maybe a
very very small number something like
that so that you can't go below the
surface of the water or the ground or
whatever you have that's totally up to
you
now we have our rotation good now we
need to work on the zoom so for zooming
I'm going to have a maximum and a
minimum zoom so we can't zoom in too far
or too far away and we're gonna have a
zoom speed how quickly the camera will
zoom in and out as we scroll the wheel
and then this variable zoom is going to
keep track of our current zoom levels so
we know what to change so we're going to
capture the zoom with unhandled input
and this is so that we will capture any
gooey stuff before this so you have if
you have a gooey overlay when you're
scrolling in a scroll box or something
like that you're not also zooming the
camera and so we have two events here we
have the cam zoom in and the camera zoom
out and zoom in is going to take our
zoom amount and we're gonna subtract
zoom speed and then zooming out is the
opposite we just add the Zoom speed and
then we set and then we're gonna clamp
it between the minimum and the maximum
so it doesn't ever go outside those
limits so how are we going to zoom it
we're gonna do it by changing the scale
of the gimbal system so scale equals
vector three one times zoom so we just
zoom equally in all directions now what
that's gonna look like is this let's go
up a little bit now as I click the mouse
you can see the increment right
a little bit by each click of the mouse
wheel but it's a little bit that makes
for a little bit of a jerky a factor
especially when you're close by so we
can make that better by using lerp to
interpolate our zoom as it goes we're
going to do that in the process will say
scale equals and we'll alert the scale
up to what we wanted it to lerp to which
was that by our zoom speed amount and
that's gonna make for a much smoother
zoom effect you can even see that at the
beginning when it zooms to the initial
amount and now we have a nice smooth
zoom that we can use while we're
rotating the camera around so that's it
and we could stop there and say we're
happy with the gimbal camera that we
have but some of you may want to also be
able to control the camera with the
mouse instead of the keys so I'm going
to show you how to do that as well
another variable here called mouse
control that we can set to true or false
whether we want to be using the mouse or
the keyboard and then mouse sensitivity
is going to be some amount that we can
adjust to make the mounts more or less
sensitive and so now in our process here
where we're getting the keyboard input
if Mouse control is true we want to not
capture those keyboard events and then
we're gonna go here into our unhandled
input and we're going to check for some
Mouse events so if Mouse control is true
and we get an input event mouse motion
then we know the mouse moved so we need
to capture the two axes of the mouse
movement at the x axis of the mouse is
the left and right that's going to be
our Y rotation of the gimbal and the y
axis
the mouse is going to be up and down so
that's going to be our X rotation of our
inner gimbal so if event dot relative
dot X is not zero then we must have
moved the mouse side-to-side so we're
going to do rotate l'objet object local
around the up and when we rotate by
event relative X how much we move to the
mouse x the mouse sensitivity and then
the alternative is that we move the
mouse up and down so if we also check
that the y axis of the mouse then we're
gonna rotate the inner gimbal I'm just
gonna go down here and grab that command
note that that by event dot relative
about Y times mouse sensitivity and now
if we try this out you'll see that we
can move the mouse up and down left and
right and control the camera now
something else you'll notice is that if
you move the mouse really quickly you're
going to have a problem with our clamp
that's stopping the movement so if I
move up you can see I'm stopping at the
limits but I move quickly I can snap
through there and once I've done that
now I'm stuck there unless I move
quickly again and that's because our
movement with the mouse can potentially
be very very high this event dot
relative dot Y could be a large number
so we're rotating by a large angle which
since and goers are circular it's going
to clamp us to the wrong side of the 90
degrees then we wanted and so we can fix
that by capping our amount of movement
so I'm going to make a variable here
right Y rotation and there's going to
clamp the event relative x dot y between
- values about there again that's
another one you can play with depending
on your size of your screen and and the
sensitivity of your mouse but this is
good enough for a an example and then
we're gonna say Y rotation times mouse
sensitivity and now that'll stop that
from moving too quickly when we move the
mouse really quickly so one other thing
I've added here before we wrap up is two
flags here to invert the X and y axis if
you want the mouse movement to be the
opposite of the direction it is now
which people often want for different
projects so here what we're doing is
we're just going to make a direction
variable we'll make it equal to one if
in vertex is true otherwise we'll make
it negative one and then that way we can
multiply by direction in the rotation
and it will rotate in the opposite
direction that it was doing before
that'll do it for this camera gimbal
tutorial as I said at the beginning this
is only one of many possible camera
control schemes so keep an eye out on
this channel for more tutorials on other
methods of camera control if you want a
little bit more detail I've linked in
the description below to the text
version of this tutorial on my go-to
recipes website where you can see a full
version of the script where I've added
in export properties for all of the
different values so that you can have a
nice interface over here in the
inspector to turn on and off and set
different properties thanks for watching
and I'll see you in the next video this
tutorial is part of my new Godot recipes
website the goal is to collect all the
best tips and lessons to help make you a
better go to a developer if you like
this video I hope you'll go and check
out the site and make sure to hit
subscribe so you'll be notified whenever
I release new videos thanks for watching